<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../css/tei_oxygen.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../css/tei.lex0.odd.css"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="header">
   <head>Header</head>
   <div>
      <head>General remarks</head>
      <p>A lexical resource encoded in TEI Lex-0 must, like any TEI file, start with the root
            <gi>TEI</gi> element, which, in turn, must contain a <gi>teiHeader</gi> element.</p>
      <p>TEI Lex-0, unlike TEI P5, however, requires the <code>@type</code> attribute on the root
            <code>TEI</code> with the value "lex-0". </p>
      <p>A TEI header contains information about the lexical resource itself, its source(s), its
         encoding, and its revisions. Proper, structured metadata of this kind is equally important
         for scholars using the resource, for software processing them, and for cataloguers in
         libraries and archives.</p>
      <p>The TEI header of a lexical resource has five major parts:<list>
            <item>a <hi rend="italic">file description</hi>, tagged <gi>fileDesc</gi>, provides a
               full bibliographic description of the electronic lexical resource itself as well as
               the source(s), analogue or digital, from which it may have been derived. For details,
               see section <ref target="#file-description">File Description</ref> below. </item>
            <item>an <hi rend="italic">encoding description</hi>, tagged <gi>encodingDesc</gi>,
               describes the relationship between the electronic resource and its source(s). It
               allows for detailed description of whether (or how) the electronic resource was
               produced, transcribed or normalized, how the encoder resolved ambiguities in the
               source, what levels of encoding or analysis were applied etc.</item>
            <item>a <hi rend="italic">profile description</hi>, tagged <gi>profileDesc</gi>,
               contains classificatory and contextual information about the lexical resource
               including its object and working languages.</item>
            <item>a <hi rend="italic">container for external metadata</hi>, tagged
               <gi>xenoData</gi>, contains metadata from non-TEI schemas, for instance Dublin Core,
               MARCXML or MODS, if available.</item>
            <item>a <hi rend="italic">revision history</hi>, tagged <gi>revisionDesc</gi>, contains
               a list of changes made during the development of the lexical resource, both before
               and after its official release. </item>
         </list></p>
      <p>Of these, two elements are required in TEI Lex-0: <gi>fileDesc</gi> and
            <gi>profileDesc</gi>. It is highly recommended to include additional information in
            <gi>encodingDesc</gi>. It is also an example of good practice to record changes in
            <gi>revisionDesc</gi>. </p>
   </div>
   <div xml:id="file-description">
      <head>File description</head>
      <p>The bibliographic description of the given machine-readable lexical resource is absolutely
         essential for identifying the basic information about the resource itself, its creators and
         publishers as well as the conditions under which it is made available to the public. </p>
      <p> The elements that make up <gi>fileDesc</gi> are: <specList>
            <specDesc key="titleStmt"/>
            <specDesc key="editionStmt"/>
            <specDesc key="extent"/>
            <specDesc key="publicationStmt"/>
            <specDesc key="seriesStmt"/>
            <specDesc key="sourceDesc"/>
         </specList>
      </p>
      <p><gi>fileDesc</gi> is a mandatory element in plain TEI as well, but in TEI Lex-0 there are
         some additional constraints and recommendations related to the content of this element.</p>
      <p>
         <list>
            <item>In <gi>titleStmt</gi>, TEI Lex-0 <hi rend="italic">recommends</hi> the use of
                  <att>type</att> on <gi>title</gi> (with values either <val>full</val> or
                  <val>abbr</val>) to record both the full bibliographic title of the lexicographic
               resource and the preferred abbreviated title for easy reference, should one exist.
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <titleStmt>
                     <title type="full">Lexicon Serbico-Germanico-Latinum</title>
                     <title type="abbr">LSGL</title>
                  </titleStmt>
               </egXML>
            </item>
            <item>In <gi>titleStmt</gi>, TEI Lex-0 <hi rend="italic">recommends</hi> the use of
                  <gi>persName</gi> and <gi>orgName</gi> to distinguish between the names of persons
               and organizations. This is especially important since in some cases, the name of an
               institution is used to take up the collective authorship of a work.</item>
            <item>When using <gi>persName</gi>, TEI Lex-0 <hi rend="italic">recommends</hi> to
               further structure the name with elements <gi>forename</gi> and
               <gi>surname</gi>.</item>
            <item>In <gi>publicationStmt</gi>, TEI Lex-0 <hi rend="italic">requires</hi> the use of
                  <gi>availability</gi> to record the <gi>licence</gi> of the given lexicographic
               resource. In other words, a TEI Lex-0 <hi rend="italic">must</hi> include explicit
               information on the conditions under which the given resource can be used. <egXML
                  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#StčS"><xi:include
                     href="../TEILex0.examples/headers/StčS.stripped.xml"
                     corresp="../TEILex0.examples/headers/StčS.xml" xpointer="element(/1/1/1/2)"/>
               </egXML>
            </item>
            <item>In addition to <gi>publisher</gi> and <gi>distributor</gi>, the
                  <gi>publicationStmt</gi> in TEI Lex-0 <hi rend="italic">may</hi> include
               information on any other <gi>authority</gi> responsible for creating or making the
               resource available. </item>
            <item>If using <gi>authority</gi>, TEI Lex-0 <hi rend="italic">requires</hi> the use of
                  <att>role</att> with values <val>funder</val>, <val>sponsor</val> or
                  <val>rightsHolder</val>.</item>
         </list>
      </p>
      <div>
         <head>Source description</head>
         <p>In TEI Lex-0, <gi>sourceDesc</gi> is an optional element. Born-digital resources or
            those which cannot be properly sourced do not require a <gi>sourceDesc</gi>. </p>
         <p>If a resource <hi rend="italic">is</hi> sourced, <gi>sourceDesc</gi> in TEI Lex-0
            requires that the sources be grouped in <gi>listBibl</gi> elements: <list>
               <item><code>&lt;listBibl type=&quot;dictionaries&quot;&gt;&lt;/listBibl&gt;</code>
                  lists all the dictionaries that were used as a source for the given dictionary; if
                  you are retrodigitizing a print dictionary, your <gi>listBibl</gi> may include
                  only one <gi>biblStruct</gi> with the bibliographic information about your print
                  source;</item>
               <item><code>&lt;listBibl type=&quot;literature&quot;&gt;&lt;/listBibl&gt;</code>
                  groups all the literature: for instance, all the sources used by the dictionary
                  author to illustrate examples;</item>
               <item><code>&lt;listBibl type=&quot;corpora&quot;&gt;&lt;/listBibl&gt;</code> groups
                  the information on all the corpora that were used in the production of the given
                  lexicographic resource.</item>
            </list>
         </p>
         <p>TEI Lex-0 requires the use of <gi>biblStruct</gi> for structuring
            bibliographic information about each individual source. This, too, is a departure from
            vanilla TEI which is more permissive in this respect. <list type="examples">
               <item>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#VOLP">
                     <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/headers/VOLP.stripped.xml"
                        corresp="../TEILex0.examples/headers/VOLP.xml" xpointer="element(/1/1/1/3)"
                     />
                  </egXML>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#EtymWB-XML">
                     <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/headers/EtymWB-XML.stripped.xml"
                        corresp="../TEILex0.examples/headers/EtymWB-XML.stripped.xml"
                        xpointer="element(/1/1/1/4)"/>
                  </egXML>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#StčS">
                     <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/headers/StčS.stripped.xml"
                        corresp="../TEILex0.examples/headers/StčS.xml" xpointer="element(/1/1/1/3)"
                     />
                  </egXML>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#Morais1789">
                     <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/headers/Morais.stripped.xml"
                        corresp="../TEILex0.examples/headers/Morais.xml"
                        xpointer="element(/1/1/1/4)"/>
                  </egXML>
               </item>
            </list>
         </p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div xml:id="encodingDescription">
      <head>Encoding description</head>
      <p><gi>encodingDesc</gi> is an optional element, which can be used to document the methods and
         editorial principles which governed the transcription or encoding of the lexicographic
         resource in hand and may also include sets of coded definitions used elsewhere in the
         text.</p>
      <p>For an explanation of how to encode a taxonomy of domain labels to be used for encoding
         usage labels, see section on <ref target="#HierarchicalUsageLabels">hierarchical usage
            labels</ref>. </p>
   </div>
   <div xml:id="profile-description">
      <head>Profile description</head>
      <p>In plain TEI, <gi>profileDesc</gi> is an optional element, whereas in TEI Lex-0, it is
         required. This is because the nature lexicographic resources is such that it is essential
         to identify and record the language(s) used as part of the resource metadata. </p>
      <p>That's why <gi>profileDesc</gi> requires <gi>langUsage</gi> and <gi>langUsage</gi> requires
         at least one <gi>language</gi> element.</p>
      <p>Regarding the use of the required attribute <att>role</att> and its possible values
            (<val>objectLanguage</val>, <val>workingLanguage</val>, <val>sourceLanguage</val> or
            <val>targetLanguage</val>), see the specification details for <gi>language</gi>. </p>
   </div>
   <div>
      <head>Revision description</head>
      <p><gi>revisionDesc</gi> is optional in both TEI and TEI Lex-0. The element is used to
         document the revision history of the given file. For each recorded revision, one should use
         the <gi>change</gi> element , together with the appropriate attributes: <att>when</att> to
         indicate the date of the implemented change, <att>resp</att> to assign responsibility and
            <att>n</att> to assign a number to the particular change, </p>
   </div>
</div>
