<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../css/tei_oxygen.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../css/tei.lex0.odd.css"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xml:id="introduction">
    <head>Introduction</head>
    <div>
        <head>TEI Lex-0 in a nutshell</head>
        <p>TEI Lex-0 is both a technical specification and a set of community-based recommendations
            for encoding machine-readable dictionaries. It is rooted in the <ref
                target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/index.html"> Guidelines
                of the Text Encoding Initiative</ref> (TEI) and delivered as a customization of the
            TEI schema.</p>
        <p>Following the spirit of TEI Analytics, developed in the context of the MONK project <ref
                type="cit" target="#Zillig2009">(Zillig 2009)</ref>, TEI Lex-0 aims at establishing
            a baseline encoding and a target format to facilitate the interoperability of
            heterogeneously encoded lexical resources. This is important both in the context of
            building lexical infrastructures as such <ref type="cit" target="#Ermolaev2012"
                >(Ermolaev and Tasovac 2012)</ref> and in the context of developing generic
            TEI-aware tools such as dictionary viewers and profilers. </p>
    </div>
    <div>
        <head>The community</head>
        <p>Preliminary work for the establishment of TEI Lex-0 started in the Working Group
            "Retrodigitised Dictionaries" lead by Toma Tasovac and Vera Hildenbrandt as part of the
            COST Action <ref target="http://www.elexicography.eu">European Network of
                e-Lexicography</ref> (ENeL). Upon the completion of the COST Action, the work on TEI Lex-0 was taken up by the DARIAH Working Group "Lexical Resources". Currently, the work
            on TEI Lex-0 is conducted by the DARIAH WG "Lexical Resources" (see below) with the
            support of the H2020-funded <ref target="https://elex.is">European Lexicographic
                Infrastructure</ref> (ELEXIS). </p>

        <div>
            <head>Working Group</head>
            <p>The DARIAH Working Group on Lexical Resources is a self-organized scholarly community
                working under the auspicies of the pan-European Digital Research Infrastructure for
                Arts and Humanities (DARIAH-EU). The goals of the WG are: <list>
                    <item>to explore, assess and recommend standard tools and methods for the
                        creation, application and dissemination of born-digital and retro-digitized
                        lexical resources (dictionaries, lexicons, thesauri, word lists etc.) as
                        well as other, similar kinds of structured data (gazetteers, almanacs,
                        encyclopaedias etc.); and</item>
                    <item>to foster, develop and publicize digitally-enabled lexicographic research
                        from a cross-disciplinary and transnational perspective.</item>
                </list>
            </p>
            <p>The WG focuses on the application and explication of existing standards, both
                onomasiological (TMF, TBX and SKOS) and semasiological (LMF, TEI, and Ontolex);
                draws upon the expertise of various DARIAH partners who are active in this field;
                and collaborates with relevant external projects and associations, such as the
                European Lexicographic Infrastructure (ELEXIS) and CLARIN in order to ascertain the
                widest possible reach of the Working Group’s results.</p>
            <p>At the same time, the WG pursues a strong research-driven agenda on the diversity of
                European lexicographic heritage. In addition to investigating pan-European
                vocabularies and multiple dimensions of lexical borrowing, the working group
                evaluates current practices and formulates guidelines on data enrichment and mutual
                linking of existing electronic dictionaries in view of their common European
                heritage.</p>

        </div>
        <div>
            <head>WG Chairs</head>
            <p>
                <figure type="thumbnail">
                    <graphic url="images/Laurent_Romary.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <hi rend="bold">Laurent Romary</hi> is Directeur de Recherche at Inria (team
                ALMAnaCH (France)), France. He received a PhD degree in computational linguistics in
                1989 and his Habilitation in 1999. He carries out research on the modelling of
                semi-structured documents, with a specific emphasis on texts and linguistic
                resources. He has been active in standardisation activities with ISO, as chair of
                committee ISO/TC 37/SC 4 (2002-2014), chair of ISO/TC 37 (2016-) and the Text
                Encoding Initiative, as member (2001-2011) and chair (2008-2011) of its Technical
                Council. He also has a long-standing implication in open science related
                activities.</p>
            <p><figure type="thumbnail">
                    <graphic url="images/Toma_Tasovac.jpg"/>
                </figure><hi rend="bold">Toma Tasovac</hi> is Director of the Belgrade Center for
                Digital Humanities (BCDH) and a Director of DARIAH-EU. He was educated at Harvard
                University, Princeton University and Trinity College Dublin. His areas of interest
                include lexicography, data modeling, TEI, digital editions and research
                infrastructures. He previously served as the National Coordinator of DARIAH-RS and
                Chair of the National Coordinators' Committee at DARIAH-EU. Under Toma's leadership,
                BCDH has received funding from various national and international granting bodies,
                including Erasmus Plus and Horizon 2020.</p>
        </div>

        <div>
            <head> Meetings</head>

            <p>The Working Group has organized a number of working meetings dedicated to the
                development of TEI Lex-0. These include: <list>
                    <item>Toward Best Practice Guidelines for Encoding Legacy
                            Dictionaries: An ENeL-DARIAH-PARTHENOS Expert Workshop. Preußische
                        Staatsbibliothek, Berlin (17-19 November 2016).</item>
                    <item>Overview of Retrodigitized Dictionaries and
                            Best-Practice Guidelines For Encoding Legacy Dictionaries. ENeL
                        Annual Meeting, Budapest (24 February 2017). </item>
                    <item>TEI Lex-0 @DARIAH WG "Lexical Resources". Harnack
                        Haus, Freie Universität Berlin (27 April 2017).</item>
                    <item>TEI Lex-0 @DARIAH WG "Lexical Resources". Austrian
                        Center for Digital Humanities, Austrian Academy of Sciences, Vienna (26 June
                        2017).</item>
                    <item>TEI Lex-0: From Best-Practice Guidelines to a TEI
                            Schema. DARIAH-EU Coordination Office, Berlin (2-3 May 2018).
                        Funded by DARIAH-EU's Working Groups Funding Scheme and ELEXIS.</item>
                    <item>TEI Lex-0 and Beyond: A Workshop. University of
                        Ljubljana (16 July 2018). Funded by DARIAH-EU's Working Group Funding Scheme
                        and ELEXIS.</item>
                    <item>TEI Lex-0 Meeting. DARIAH-EU Coordination Office,
                        Berlin (30 January 2019).</item>
                    <item>Joint TEI Lex-0 / Ontolex-Lemon Meeting. Collocated
                        with <ref target="https://elex.link/elex2019/">eLex 2019</ref>. Sintra,
                        Portugal (4 October 2019). Funded by ELEXIS.</item>
                    <item>Toward a TEI Lex-0 Publisher: A Workshop, DARIAH-EU
                        Coordination Office, Berlin (16-17 December 2019). Funded by the Belgrade
                        Center for Digital Humanities.</item>
                </list>
            </p>
</div><div>
    <head>Training measures</head>
    <p>TODO: list training measures</p>
            <figure type="gallery" xml:id="community-effort">
                <head>TEI Lex-0 would not be possible without joint community effort</head>
                <graphic url="https://i.imgur.com/XAMQknR.jpg" rend="pure-u-2-3 top-left"/>
                <graphic url="https://i.imgur.com/DfL7CWY.jpgg" rend="pure-u-1-3 top-right"/>
                <graphic url="https://i.imgur.com/UVXnDSy.jpg" rend="pure-u-1-1" height="400px"/>
                <graphic url="https://i.imgur.com/qEb4eED.jpg" rend="pure-u-1-3"/>
                <graphic url="https://i.imgur.com/oun5VsX.jpg" rend="pure-u-2-3"/>
                <graphic url="https://i.imgur.com/i5VmV4m.jpg" rend="pure-u-2-3"/>
                <graphic url="https://i.imgur.com/6NSzMJ6.jpg" rend="pure-u-1-3"/>
                <graphic url="https://i.imgur.com/vfxQiYx.png" rend="pure-u-1-1"/>
                <graphic url="https://i.imgur.com/Wlf8GoD.jpg" rend="pure-u-1-3"/>
                <graphic url="https://i.imgur.com/LaCPF0q.jpg" rend="pure-u-2-3"/>
                <!-- https://i.imgur.com/GThOWKf.jpg-->
                <graphic url="https://i.imgur.com/KWLmMyY.jpg" rend="pure-u-3-4"/>
                <graphic url="https://i.imgur.com/tObvruE.png" rend="pure-u-1-4"/>
                <graphic url="https://i.imgur.com/mMkp4g6.jpg" rend="pure-u-1-3 bottom-left"/>
                <graphic url="https://i.imgur.com/cp4MKJd.jpg" rend="pure-u-2-3 bottom-right"/>
            </figure>

        </div>


        <!--the following will generate a list of contributors in alphabetic order from the teiHeader-->
        <divGen type="contributors"/>

    </div>

    <div>
        <head>The rationale</head>
        <p>To what extent can we achieve consistent encoding within a given community of practice by
            following the TEI Guidelines? The topic is of particular importance for lexical data if
            we think of the potential wealth of content we could gain from pooling together the
            information available in the variety of highly structured, historical and contemporary
            lexical resources. The encoding possibilities offered by the Dictionaries Chapter in the
            Guidelines are too numerous and too flexible to guarantee sufficient interoperability
            and a coherent model for searching, visualising or enriching multiple lexical
            resources.</p>
        <p>TEI Lex-0 should not be thought of as a replacement of the <ref
                target="https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/DI.html">Dictionaries
                Chapter</ref> in the TEI Guidelines or as the format that must be necessarily used
            for editing or managing individual resources, especially in those projects and/or
            institutions that already have established workflows based on their own flavors of TEI.
            TEI Lex-0 should be primarily seen as a format that existing TEI dictionaries can be
            unequivocally transformed to in order to be queried, visualised, or mined in a uniform
            way. At the same time, however, there is no reason why TEI Lex-0 could not or should not
            be used as a best-practice example in educational settings or as a foundation of new
            TEI-based projects. This is especially true considering the fact that TEI Lex-0 aims to
            to stay as aligned as possible with the TEI subset developed in conjunction with the
            revision of the ISO LMF (Lexical Markup Framework) standard (cf. <ref
                target="#Romary2015">Romary 2015</ref>)</p>

    </div>
   
</div>
