<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../css/tei_oxygen.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../css/tei.lex0.odd.css"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="forms">
    <head>Forms</head>
    <p>The current TEI <hi rend="italic">Guidelines</hi> allows for an extremely wide range of
        encoding possibilities for written and spoken forms. In the discussion which follows, we
        suggest ways in which the elements, in particular <gi>form</gi>, can be constrained. We give
        examples of use types not covered by the <hi rend="italic">Guidelines</hi>, and propose some
        extensions.</p>
    <div>
        <head>A note on inheritance</head>
        <p>We assume that in order to determine the complete properties of an element inside the
            entry tree, the principle of default inheritance applies, e.g. grammatical properties of
            a form are determined by collecting the sibling <gi>gramGrp</gi> of the ancestor-or-self
            of the focus element, where the superordinate grammatical properties can be overwritten
            by the lower-level properties. This principle is relatively straightforward in the case
            of grammatical properties, but more complex for the word paradigm, esp. in cases of
            variant forms. For more information c.f. Ide et al. (<ref
                target="https://www.kilgarriff.co.uk/Publications/2000-IdeKilgRomary-Euralex.pdf"
                    ><hi>2000</hi></ref>) and Erjavec et al. (<ref
                target="http://www.lrec-conf.org/proceedings/lrec2000/html/summary/335.htm"
                    ><hi>2000</hi></ref>).</p>
    </div>
    <div>
        <head>Lemmas</head>
        <p>The form element should always be qualified by its <att>type</att>. The lemma (i.e.
            headword) form should be encoded as <code rend="language-xpath"
                >form[@type="lemma"]</code>.</p>
        <p>If it is necessary to specify the grammatical properties of the lemma form itself (as
            opposed to the grammatical properties of the entry), this is described by <code
                rend="language-xpath">entry/form[@type="lemma"]/gramGrp</code>.</p>
    </div>
    <div>
        <head>Inflected forms</head>
        <p>Dictionaries often include additional forms next to the lemma. In English, these are used
            to specify irregular forms, such as “corpus / corpora” or “take / took”, whereas in
            inflectionally rich languages they are often used to help the user determine the correct
            paradigm of the word. </p>
        <p>Such inflected forms should be encoded in <code rend="language-xpath"
                >entry/form[@type="inflected"]</code>, e.g.:</p>
        <figure>
            <graphic url="https://i.imgur.com/JxXgsjl.jpg"/>
        </figure>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#Chambers2014">
            <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml"
                corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="CH.go1"/>
        </egXML>
        <p>Or take this example: <hi rend="bold">abeceda, -y</hi>: in Czech, "-y" is a genitive
            singular suffix for feminine nouns. We can mark-up the grammatical properties of the
            suffix, while providing the full form of the noun as well:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml"
                corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="en000008"/>
        </egXML>
    </div>
    <div>
        <head>Paradigms</head>
        <p>When several inflected forms can be present next to the lemma, these can be embedded into
                <code rend="langauge-xpath">entry/form[@type="paradigm"]</code>. The decision on
            whether to use this extra element depends on the particular dictionary and language.</p>
        <p>The other use case for paradigms is when the full inflectional paradigm of the word is
            embedded in the entry, i.e. when the dictionary also includes all the word-forms of the
            words covered, which can be useful for example in machine processing. </p>
        <p>An entry may contain several paradigms, e.g. a partial one for humans and a full one for
            machines, or one for each stem of a verb. Each paradigm type should be distinguished by
            the <att>subtype</att> attribute.</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml"
                corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="perder"/>
        </egXML>
    </div>
    <div>
        <head>Variants</head>
        <p>The representation of variation within a form is highly dependant upon the specifics of
            the features of the variation and the way in which they vary. However, as a general
            principle, variation may be encoded as <code rend="language-xpath"
                >form[@type="variant"]</code> and embedded within the parent element for which a
            subordinate feature exhibits variation.</p>
        <div>
            <head>Orthographic variation</head>
            <p>Several kinds of orthographic variation may be distinguished. Below, we present some
                of the options with the corresponding examples.</p>
            <p>Spelling variation due to change in language’s orthography convention:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml"
                    corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="Flussschifffahrt"/>
            </egXML>
            <p>The following example is from American English in which due to the lack of official
                conventions for transliteration of Arabic orthography to the English (Latin) script,
                the initial vowel in the surname ‘Osama Bin Laden’ varies between ‘O’ and ‘U’:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml"
                    corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="Osama"/>
            </egXML>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head>Phonetic variation</head>
            <p>In this example, the entry contains the single orthographic form as a direct child of
                the lemma and phonetic transcriptions of the two roughly equally used variant
                pronunciations of the word 'caramel' from American English.</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="caramel-prons">
                <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml"
                    corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="caramel-en"/>
            </egXML>
            <floatingText type="inFocusPanel" xml:id="multiple-variants">
                <body>
                    <head>multiple variants</head>
                    <p>In the example <ref target="#caramel-prons">above</ref>, one could have
                        chosen to mark up two different pronunciations using two <gi>pron</gi>
                        elements inside the <code rend="language-xpath">form[@type="lemma"]</code>.
                        Considering, however, that each individual pronunciation could, in theory,
                        be further qualified, for instance, by a <gi>usg</gi> note, indicating the
                        geographic area in which the said pronunciation is used, TEI Lex-0
                        recommends that multiple variants, whether orthographic or orthoepic, be
                        contained each in its own <gi>form</gi> element.</p>
                </body>
            </floatingText>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head>Regional or dialectal variation</head>
            <p> In the following example from Mixtepec-Mixtec, there is variation in the form of the
                word for the city of Oaxaca between speakers from the village of Yucanany and the
                rest of the speakers. Since the Yucanany variety makes up only a small portion of
                the speakers of the language, this case of variation is represented as an embedded
                    <code rend="language-xpath">form[@type="variant"]</code> within the lemma. Note
                the use of <code rend="language-xpath">usg[@type="geographic"]/placeName</code> to
                explicitly specify this feature in addition to the use of the private language
                subtag (<code rend="language-xpath">@xml:lang="mix-x-YCNY"</code>) as per <ref>BCP
                    47</ref>.</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml"
                    corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="Oaxaca-MIX"/>
            </egXML>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div>
        <head>Condensed forms</head>
        <p>In some lexicographic traditions, it is common to encounter dictionary entries that
            conflate two or more distinct lemmas into a single entry headword. A frequent example of
            this is the combination of a base verb and its reflexive variant in Savic languages.
            While such pairings may suggest morphological or derivational relationships, they are
            more than just inflectional variants: they can sometimes represent distinct lexical
            items, each with its own semantics and usage. </p>
        <p>To illustrate this phenomenon, consider the Old Czech verb <code>leleti</code> and its
            reflexive counterpart <code>leleti sě</code>. These can be presented in a print
            dictionary in a condensed, shorthand form such as <code>leleti (sě)</code>.</p>
        <figure>
            <graphic url="https://imgur.com/Dm57uLO.png" rend="padded"/>
        </figure>
        <p>In English, this would be comparable to a hypothetical lemma <code>ask (oneself)</code>
            combining <code>ask</code> (“to pose a question”) and <code>ask oneself</code> (“to
            wonder, to reflect”) in a single entry as one condensed lemma.</p>
        <p>Because bracketed constructions such as <code>leleti (sě)</code> do not represent
            naturally occurring word forms, we recommend treating these condensed forms as labels (<gi>lbl</gi>)
            rather than lemmas. From an encoding perspective, this means using <code>lbl[@type="condensedLemma"]</code> to
            represent the compacted headword for display or identification purposes, while defining
            each of the component lemmas separately using individual <gi>form</gi> elements:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#MSS">
            <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml"
                corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="MSS.leleti"/>
        </egXML>
        <p>Above, the <att>value</att> attribute is used to supply reconstructed or editorially
            inferred lemma forms that do <hi rend="italic">not</hi> appear explicitly in the print
            source. This distinction is crucial for digital representations of legacy lexica, where
            not all valid headwords are explicitly listed in the original. In TEI Lex-0, it is
            common to encode lemmas that are not physically present in the printed source using the
                <att>value</att> attribute on <gi>orth</gi>, rather than placing the text directly
            as content within the element.</p>
        <floatingText type="inFocusPanel" xml:id="indexing-condensed-lemmas">
            <body>
                <head>indexing condensed lemmas</head>
                <p>If we encode regular lemmas (those present in the source) as
                        <code>//form[@type='lemma']/orth</code> and reconstructed lemmas (those
                    inferred or editorially supplied) as
                        <code>//form[@type='lemma']/orth/@value</code>, we will no longer have a
                    uniform path for indexing the dictionary. This is because two kinds of lemmas
                    will reside on different XPaths. This, however, is a necessary and principled
                    compromise.</p>
                <p>The suggested encoding and expansion of condensed lemmas allow users
                    and systems to reconstruct the full lemma inventory of a dictionary, including
                    analytically significant forms absent from the source. At the same time, they
                    make explicit which forms are present in the original and which have been
                    editorially supplied, thus preserving presentational fidelity to the print source while enhancing
                    searchability, machine processing, and downstream applications.</p>
                <p>To support robust querying, it is, therefore, recommended that documentation or downstream
                    systems account for this distinction, for instance by using the combined XPath
                    expression such as <code>//form[@type='lemma']/orth/text() |
                        //form[@type='lemma']/orth/@value</code> to get to the consolidated list of
                    both explicit and implicit lemmas.</p>
            </body>
        </floatingText>
    </div>
    <div>
        <head>Multiword expressions</head>
        <p>The Dictionary Chapter of the TEI Guidelines is very sparse when it comes to
            recommendations for encoding polylexical units. The only mention of the adjective
            “multi-word” appears in the definition of the element <gi>term</gi>: “contains a
            single-word, multi-word, or symbolic designation which is regarded as a technical term”
            but this is not relevant for the encoding of polylexical units in general-purpose
            dictionaries.</p>
        <p>TEI includes an element <gi>colloc</gi> (collocate), which is defined as containing “any
            sequence of words that co-occur with the headword with significant frequency” but, in a
            different example, “colloc” is used as an attribute value for the element <gi>usg</gi>
            (usage). It is precisely this type of ambiguity that TEI Lex-0 is trying to resolve.</p>
        <p>The TEI Guidelines recommend the use of <gi>re</gi> (related entry) to encode “related
            entries for direct derivatives or inflected forms of the entry word, or for compound
            words, phrases, collocations, and idioms containing the entry word” with barely any
            useful examples, or discussion of how to encode different types of polylexical units.
            TEI Lex-0, on the other hand, does not include <gi>re</gi>. In TEI Lex-0, <gi>entry</gi>
            was made recursive in order to account for nestable entry-like structures without the
            need to resort to <gi>re</gi>, a differently named element whose content model would be
            indistinguishable from <gi>entry</gi> itself. Eventually, the new content model of
                <gi>entry</gi>, which allows nesting, was adopted by TEI itself (<ref
                target="#Tasovac2020">Tasovac 2020</ref>).</p>
        <p>TODO: explain different types of mwe's from a dict. model perspective referring to <ref
                target="#Tasovac2020">Tasovac 2020</ref>)</p>
        <div>
            <head>Collocations</head>
            <p>TODO: explain "lexicographically transparent"</p>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="https://imgur.com/gcsqdhb.jpg" rend="padded"/>
            </figure>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#DLPC2014">
                <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml"
                    corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="DLPC.descalçar"/>
            </egXML>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head>Idiomatic expressions</head>
            <p>TODO text ("lexicographically non-transparent")</p>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="https://i.imgur.com/VXwxggA.jpg" rend="padded"/>
            </figure>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#DLPC2014">
                <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml"
                    corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="DLPC.bombeiro"/>
            </egXML>
        </div>
    </div>
</div>
