<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../css/tei_oxygen.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../css/tei.lex0.odd.css"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="forms">
    <head>Forms</head>
    <p>The current TEI <hi rend="italic">Guidelines</hi> allows for an extremely wide range of
        encoding possibilities for written and spoken forms. In the discussion which follows, we
        suggest ways in which the elements, in particular <gi>form</gi>, can be constrained. We give
        examples of use types not covered by the <hi rend="italic">Guidelines</hi>, and propose some
        extensions.</p>
    <div>
        <head>A note on inheritance</head>
        <p>We assume that in order to determine the complete properties of an element inside the
            entry tree, the principle of default inheritance applies, e.g. grammatical properties of
            a form are determined by collecting the sibling <gi>gramGrp</gi> of the ancestor-or-self
            of the focus element, where the superordinate grammatical properties can be overwritten
            by the lower-level properties. This principle is relatively straightforward in the case
            of grammatical properties, but more complex for the word paradigm, esp. in cases of
            variant forms. For more information c.f. Ide et al. (<ref
                target="https://www.kilgarriff.co.uk/Publications/2000-IdeKilgRomary-Euralex.pdf"
                    ><hi>2000</hi></ref>) and Erjavec et al. (<ref
                target="http://www.lrec-conf.org/proceedings/lrec2000/html/summary/335.htm"
                    ><hi>2000</hi></ref>).</p>
    </div>
    <div>
        <head>Grammatical properties of lexical entries</head>
        <p>Grammatical properties of lexical entries should be specified in
                <code>entry/gramGrp</code>. This element will typically specify the part-of-speech
            of the entry.</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <entry xml:lang="en" type="mainEntry" xml:id="on">
                <form type="lemma"><orth>on</orth></form>
                <gramGrp>
                    <gram type="pos">prep</gram>
                </gramGrp>
                <!--...-->
            </entry>
        </egXML>
        <p>Notes:</p>
        <list type="ordered">
            <item>Grammatical properties of the entry should <hi>not</hi> be specified in
                    <code>entry/form[@type="lemma"]/gramGrp</code>
            </item>
            <item>In cases where headwords are discriminated only on the basis of their orthography
                (e.g. in English dictionaries which treat conversion pairs of nouns and verbs, such
                as <hi>run</hi>, as belonging in single entries), <code>entry/gramGrp</code> should
                not be used, because its role is taken over by the individual
                    <code>sense/gramGrp</code>. </item>
        </list>
        <figure>
            <graphic url="https://imgur.com/b9dNR9m.png"/>
        </figure>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml"
                corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="ED.aid"/>
        </egXML>
    </div>

    <div>
        <head>Representation of the lemma</head>
        <p>The form element should always be qualified by its <att>type</att>. The lemma (i.e.
            headword) form should be encoded as <code>form[@type="lemma"]</code>.</p>
        <p>If it is necessary to specify the grammatical properties of the lemma form itself (as
            opposed to the grammatical properties of the entry), this is described by
                <code>entry/form[@type="lemma"]/gramGrp</code>, e.g.:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="ROTL.1">
            <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml"
                corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="element(go/1)"/>
        </egXML>
    </div>
    <div>
        <head>Representation of inflected forms</head>
        <p>Dictionaries often include additional forms next to the lemma. In English, these are used
            to specify irregular forms, such as “corpus / corpora” or “take / took”, whereas in
            inflectionally rich languages they are often used to help the user determine the correct
            paradigm of the word (such as “abeceda / -y” in Czech). </p>
        <p>Such inflected forms should be encoded in <code>entry/form/@type="inflected"</code>,
            e.g.:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml"
                corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="go"/>
        </egXML>
        <p>Or take this example: <hi rend="bold">abeceda, -y</hi>: <code>-y</code> is a genitive
            singular suffix for feminine nouns. We can mark-up the grammatical properties of the
            suffix, while providing the full form of the noun as well:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml"
                corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="en000008"/>
        </egXML>
    </div>
    <div>
        <head>Paradigms</head>
        <p>When several inflected forms can be present next to the lemma, these can be embedded into
                <code>entry/form[@type="paradigm"]</code>. The decision on whether to use this extra
            element depends on the particular dictionary and language.</p>
        <p>The other use case for paradigms is when the full inflectional paradigm of the word is
            embedded in the entry, i.e. when the dictionary also includes all the word-forms of the
            words covered, which can be useful for example in machine processing. </p>
        <p>An entry may contain several paradigms, e.g. a partial one for humans and a full one for
            machines, or one for each stem of a verb. Each paradigm type should be distinguished by
            the <att>subtype</att> attribute.</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml"
                corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="perder"/>
        </egXML>
    </div>
    <div>
        <head>Representation of variants</head>
        <p>The representation of variation within a form is highly dependant upon the specifics of
            the features of the variation and the way in which they vary. However, as a general
            principle, variation may be encoded as <code>form[@type="variant"]</code> and embedded
            within the parent element for which a subordinate feature exhibits variation.</p>
        <div>
            <head>Orthographic variation</head>
            <p>Several kinds of orthographic variation may be distinguished. Below, we present some
                of the options with the corresponding examples.</p>
            <p>Spelling variation due to change in language’s orthography convention:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml"
                    corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="Flussschifffahrt"/>
            </egXML>

            <p>The following example is from American English in which due to the lack of official
                conventions for transliteration of Arabic orthography to the English (Latin) script,
                the initial vowel in the surname ‘Osama Bin Laden’ varies between ‘O’ and ‘U’:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml"
                    corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="Osama"/>
            </egXML>
        </div>
        <div>
            <head>Phonetic Variation</head>
            <p>In this example, the entry contains the single orthographic form as a direct child of
                the lemma and phonetic transcriptions of the two roughly equally used variant
                pronunciations of the word 'caramel' from American English.</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml"
                    corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="caramel-en"/>
            </egXML>

            <p>We have an open GitHub <ref
                    target="https://github.com/DARIAH-ERIC/lexicalresources/issues/16">issue</ref>
                related to this.</p>

        </div>
        <div>
            <head>Regional or dialectal Variation</head>
            <p> In the following example from Mixtepec-Mixtec, there is variation in the form of the
                word for the city of Oaxaca between speakers from the village of Yucanany and the
                rest of the speakers. Since the Yucanany variety makes up only a small portion of
                the speakers of the language, this case of variation is represented as an embedded
                    <code>form[@type="variant"]</code> within the lemma. Note the use of
                    <code>usg[@type="geo"]/placeName</code> to explicitly specify this feature in
                addition to the use of the private language subtag
                    (<code>xml:lang="mix-x-YCNY"</code>) as per <ref>BCP 47</ref>.</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml"
                    corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="Oaxaca-MIX"/>
            </egXML>
        </div>
    </div>
</div>
