<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../css/tei_oxygen.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../css/tei.lex0.odd.css"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="senses">
    <head>Senses</head>
    <div>
        <head>General remarks</head>
        <p>In the current TEI Dictionary Chapter, the content model of <gi>entry</gi>
            allows one to have sense-related information directly within <gi>entry</gi>.
            TEI Lex-0 proscribes a stricter use of these elements so that sense-related
            information is grouped within the <gi>sense</gi> element, in accordance with
            the underlying semasiological model implemented in the TEI <hi rend="italic"
                >Guidelines</hi>.</p>
        <p><gi>sense</gi> should be therefore considered mandatory for any dictionary
            entry that actually provides sense information for the headword. Further in
            this document, we consider some additional specific cases e.g. “referencing”
            entries (entires that simply point to other entries) and inflexional lexica
            (dictionaries that describe word forms only), where <gi>sense</gi> is not a
            mandatory child of <gi>entry</gi>.</p>
        <p>As a consequence of making the use of <gi>sense</gi> more systematic within
            <gi>entry</gi>, we have seen (see section on <gi>entry</gi>) that some
            elements are no longer allowed as children of <gi>entry</gi>. We provide
            here a specific background for each of them:</p>
        <list type="unordered">
            <item><gi>def</gi> is clearly intended to provide a prose description of a
                meaning within a <gi>sense</gi> element and should not appear in any
                other context;</item>
            <item>In the same way, it is recommended that <gi>cit</gi> be used
                exclusively as a child of <gi>sense</gi>, or when necessary within
                <gi>dictScrap</gi>;</item>
            <item>The case of <gi>hom</gi> is peculiar since it provides a subordinate
                organization to an entry which is redundant in relation to what
                <gi>sense</gi> allows one to represent. <gi>hom</gi> is not allowed
                in TEI Lex-0.</item>
        </list>
        <p>Note: In the case one has to deal with information that does not fit a
            <gi>sense</gi>-based organization, for instance in the process of
            retro-digitizing an existing dictionary source, the use of
            <gi>dictScrap</gi> is recommended. Further step in the encoding of the
            lexical content may lead to a more precise encoding in a second phase.</p>
        <p>In TEI Lex-0, <gi>sense</gi> has a mandatory <att>xml:id</att>.</p>
    </div>
    <div>
        <head>A limited number of possible contexts for <gi>def</gi></head>
        <p>In the current TEI guidelines, <gi>def</gi> is allowed to be used within the
            following elements:</p>
        <list type="unordered">
            <item>Module core: <gi>cit</gi></item>
            <item>Module dictionaries: <gi>dictScrap</gi>, <gi>entry</gi>,
                <gi>entryFree</gi>, <gi>etym</gi>, <gi>hom</gi>, <gi>re</gi>,
                <gi>sense</gi></item>
            <item>Module namesdates: <gi>nym</gi></item>
        </list>
        <p>TEI Lex-0 allows the use of <gi>def</gi> in <gi>sense</gi>, <gi>cit</gi> and
            <gi>etym</gi> only. All other existing contexts would be implemented by
            embedding <gi>def</gi> within a <gi>sense</gi>.</p>
    </div>
    <div>
        <head>Encoding sense in entries with multiple parts of speech</head>
        <p>For multi-POS lexical entries, TEI Lex-0 considers each POS as a trigger for
            a new sense. Consequently, we recommend encoding grammatical information in
            each sense coming after the first one to be serialised inside the semantic
            bloc as follows:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="d1e1022">
            <sense xml:id="xyz">
                <gramGrp>
                    <gram type="pos"><!--...--></gram>
                </gramGrp>
                <def><!--...--></def>
                <!--...-->
            </sense>
        </egXML>
        <p>Consider this example, where <mentioned>arrest</mentioned> appears both as a
            verb and a noun:</p>
        <figure>
            <graphic n="10011" width="6.720416666666667cm" height="4.709583333333334cm"
                url="https://imgur.com/zvd4oEh.png"/>
        </figure>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml"
                corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="arrest"/>
        </egXML>
    </div>
    
    <div>
        <head>Deprecating <gi>hom</gi></head>
        <p>Making a clear difference between a situation where an entry has to be split
            into two or more homonyms and one where these differences correspond to a
            semantic alternation is lexicographically difficult. Still, the main danger
            in keeping both possibilities in the representation of a lexical entry in a
            digital lexicon is to introduce a systematic structural ambiguity as to
            where the appropriate information is to be found. We thus deprecate
            <gi>hom</gi> altogether in the present recommendation and have this
            element be replaced by the appropriate <gi>sense</gi> construct. For
            instance, the following example from the TEI <hi rend="italic"
                >Guidelines</hi>:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="false">
            <entry>
                <form>
                    <orth>bray</orth>
                    <pron>breI</pron>
                </form>
                <hom>
                    <gramGrp>
                        <gram type="pos">n</gram>
                    </gramGrp>
                    <sense>
                        <def>cry of an ass; sound of a trumpet.</def>
                    </sense>
                </hom>
                <hom>
                    <gramGrp>
                        <gram type="pos">vt</gram>
                        <subc>VP2A</subc>
                    </gramGrp>
                    <sense>
                        <def>make a cry or sound of this kind.</def>
                    </sense>
                </hom>
            </entry>
        </egXML>
        <p>would in TEI Lex-0 be represented as:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml"
                corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="bray"/>
        </egXML>
    </div>
</div>

