<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../css/tei_oxygen.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../css/tei.lex0.odd.css"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="senses">
    <head>Senses</head>
    <div>
        <head>General remarks</head>
        <p>In the current TEI Dictionary Chapter, the content model of <gi>entry</gi> allows one to
            have sense-related information directly within <gi>entry</gi>. TEI Lex-0 proscribes a
            stricter use of these elements so that sense-related information is grouped within the
                <gi>sense</gi> element, in accordance with the underlying semasiological model
            implemented in the TEI <hi rend="italic">Guidelines</hi>.</p>
        <p><gi>sense</gi> should be therefore considered mandatory for any dictionary entry that
            actually provides sense information for the headword. Further in this document, we
            consider some additional specific cases e.g. “referencing” entries (entries that simply
            point to other entries) and inflectional lexica (dictionaries that describe word forms
            only), where <gi>sense</gi> is not a mandatory child of <gi>entry</gi>.</p>
        <p>As a consequence of making the use of <gi>sense</gi> more systematic within
                <gi>entry</gi>, we have seen (see section on <gi>entry</gi>) that some elements are
            no longer allowed as children of <gi>entry</gi>. We provide here a specific background
            for each of them:</p>
        <list type="unordered">
            <item><gi>def</gi> is clearly intended to provide a prose description of a meaning
                within a <gi>sense</gi> element and should not appear in any other context;</item>
            <item>In the same way, it is recommended that <gi>cit</gi> be used exclusively as a
                child of <gi>sense</gi>, or when necessary within <gi>dictScrap</gi>;</item>
            <item>The case of <gi>hom</gi> is peculiar since it provides a subordinate organization
                to an entry which is redundant in relation to what <gi>sense</gi> allows one to
                represent. <gi>hom</gi> is not allowed in TEI Lex-0.</item>
        </list>
        <p>Note: In the case one has to deal with information that does not fit a
            <gi>sense</gi>-based organization, for instance in the process of retro-digitizing an
            existing dictionary source, the use of <gi>dictScrap</gi> is recommended. Further step
            in the encoding of the lexical content may lead to a more precise encoding in a second
            phase.</p>
        <p>In TEI Lex-0, <gi>sense</gi> has a mandatory <att>xml:id</att>.</p>
    </div>
    <div>
        <head>Limiting contexts for <gi>def</gi></head>
        <p>In the current <hi rend="italic">TEI Guidelines</hi>, <gi>def</gi> is allowed within the
            following elements:</p>
        <list type="unordered">
            <item>Module core: <gi>cit</gi></item>
            <item>Module dictionaries: <gi>dictScrap</gi>, <gi>entry</gi>, <gi>entryFree</gi>,
                    <gi>etym</gi>, <gi>hom</gi>, <gi>re</gi>, <gi>sense</gi></item>
            <item>Module namesdates: <gi>nym</gi></item>
        </list>
        <p>TEI Lex-0 allows the use of <gi>def</gi> in <gi>sense</gi> only. All other existing
            contexts would be implemented by embedding <gi>def</gi> within a <gi>sense</gi>. </p>
    </div>
    <div>
        <head>Definition or gloss?</head>
        
        <p>In TEI Lex-0, <gi>def</gi> is used only within a <gi>sense</gi> construct. <gi>gloss</gi>, on the other hand, 
            doesn't have to be a child of <gi>sense</gi>. Glosses are reserved for short semantic
            qualifications that don't meet the criteria of full-fledged lexicographic definitions.</p>
        <p>Glosses are often used in etymologies as a kind of semantic shorthand signaling the meaning of a foreign word; or in general-purpose dictionaries
            describing (but not defining) the semantic context of a word. For instance: </p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml" corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="arrest"/>
        </egXML>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="grammatical-properties-in-senses">
        <head>Grammatical properties</head>
        <p>In some dictionaries, individual dictionary senses may be associated with grammatical
            properties, such as part of speech or gender, that differ from the rest of the entry:
            for instance, a particular sense of a countable noun may be used only in plural. In such
            cases, <gi>gramGrp</gi> will be naturally placed inside the given <gi>sense</gi>: </p>
        <p>Consider, for instance, the second sense of this entry:</p>
        <figure>
            <graphic url="https://i.imgur.com/2UJC9Ae.jpg" rend="padded"/>
        </figure>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#DLPC2014" xml:id="antepassado-gramGrp-in-sense">
            <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml" corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="DLPC.antepassado_b_2"/>
        </egXML>
        <div xml:id="nested-entries-vs-multiple-senses">
            <head>Nested entries vs. multiple senses</head>
            <p>While TEI Lex-0 has been created to simplify the choices available for encoding
                various lexicographic components, certain levels of ambiguity remain, often due to
                the highly condensed nature of dictionary content.</p>
            <p>Consider, for instance, this entry: <figure>
                    <graphic url="https://i.imgur.com/LlL0H4l.jpg"/>
                </figure>
            </p>
            <p>Is this an entry with two senses? Or are these two entries that were on the account
                of typographic density merged into one?</p>
            <p>The answer is as much in the eyes of the beholder, as it is in the eyes of the
                lexicographers behind the dictionary that the entry stems from, in this case <title
                    rend="italic">The Chambers Dictionary</title>. Both the encoder <hi
                    rend="italic">and</hi> lexicographers, however, are influenced by lexicographic
                and linguistic traditions in which they operate. For an overview of the
                homonymy-polysemy dilemma, see, for instance, <ref target="#Zöfgen1989">Zöfgen
                    1989</ref>. </p>
            <p>It can't be stressed enough that the goal of dictionary encoding is not to resolve
                linguistic disputes or evaluate lexicographic traditions but rather to create
                consistent, if abstracted, representations of lexicographic architectures. </p>
            <p>So, what can we do in this particular case? Should we encode <hi rend="bold"
                    >gash</hi> as an entry consisting of senses, each with a different part of
                speech, like this:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="gash-as-grammatical-homonyms">
                        <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml" corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="CHDOEL.gash2"/>
                    </egXML>
            <p>This is surely valid TEI Lex-0. There is conceptually nothing wrong with this
                encoding: it adequately represents the structure implied by the source text.</p>
            <p> We should, however, try to look at the issue at hand from a broader, comparative,
                perspective.</p>
            <list>
                <item>In the Portuguese polysemous entry <hi rend="bold">antepassado</hi>
                    <ref target="#antepassado-gramGrp-in-sense">above</ref>, we had a case in which
                    one particular sense (used in plural only) deviated from the other senses (which
                    are used in both singular and plural). Since the senses were numbered in the
                    original, there was never any doubt about how we would encode this. It was clear
                    from the outset: <list>
                        <item>that the semantic information in that entry was grouped by a construct
                            called <gi>sense</gi>;</item>
                        <item>that senses inherited grammatical properties from the entry as a whole
                            (i.e. <code rend="language-xpath">entry/gramGrp</code>);</item>
                        <item>that, implicitly, we could assume that each sense can be used with the
                            noun in both singular and plural; and</item>
                        <item>that the plural-only sense was grammatically exceptional, hence <code
                                rend="language-xpath">entry/sense/gramGrp/</code>).</item>
                    </list>
                </item>
                <item>The English example is different: <hi rend="b">gash</hi> as a verb and as a
                    noun are grammatical homonyms. If we encode them, as we did <ref
                        target="#gash-as-grammatical-homonyms">above</ref>, as two senses within one
                    entry, we end up with an entry in which there is no inheritance (of grammatical
                    properties) and only exceptions (at each sense-level). </item>
            </list>
            <p>Because TEI Lex-0 is aimed at creating a baseline encoding to facilitate data
                exchange and comparison between different dictionaries, we, therefore, recommend to
                encode grammatical homonyms in TEI Lex-0 as nested entries and to use
                    <gi>gramGrp</gi> in <gi>sense</gi> constructs to mark up sense-specific
                deviations from the rule of grammatical inheritance. </p>
            <p>For that reason, our preferred encoding of <hi rend="bold">gash</hi> as a verb and a
                noun would be:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                    <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml" corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="CH.gash2"/>
                </egXML>
            <p>For an example in which grammatical homonyms have themselves multiple senses, one of
                which is grammatically constrained, see, for instance: </p>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="https://imgur.com/b9dNR9m.png"/>
            </figure>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                    <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml" corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="ED.aid"/>
                </egXML>
        </div>
    </div>
</div>
