<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../css/tei_oxygen.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../css/tei.lex0.odd.css"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="usage">
    <head>Usage</head>
    <p>Usage labels is a procedure which indicates that “a certain lexical item deviates in a
        certain respect from the main bulk of items described in a dictionary and that its use is
        subject to some kind of restriction” </p>
    <p>In the current TEI guidelines, <gi>usg</gi> is defined as an element which marks up “usage
        information in a dictionary entry”. Prototypically, usage information is a label which can
        be attached at various points in the entry hierarchy in order to signal restrictions in
        terms of geographic regions, domains of specialized language or stylistic properties for the
        particular lexical item that it is attached to.</p>

    <div>
        <head>Label-like vs. narrative usage descriptions</head>
        <p>Usage information ca be provided in dictionaries both in the form of label-like
            descriptors (often abbreviated) and as fuller narrative expressions.</p>
        <p>Consider, for instance, the following senses taken from a German entry for Pflaume “plum”
            where usage information is provided by labels taken from fixed sets of values for
            stylistic and diatopic properties:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml" corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="pflaume"/>
        </egXML>
        <p>In contrast to the example above, the following sample features an occurrence of a more
            verbose usage description that does not rely on a fixed vocabulary. The sample is taken
            from a Serbian dialect dictionary. The quote in the dialect is further qualified by a
            usage hint: “(said by a peasant woman in the field in hot weather)” which provides a
            particular context in which the quote was recorded.</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="USG.2" source="#Златановић2017">
            <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml" corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="element(MZ.RGJS.сејче/4/1)"/>
           
        </egXML>
    </div>
    <div>
        <head>Types of usage</head>
        <p>In TEI Lex-0, <gi>usg</gi> is a typed element and <att>type</att> is a mandatory
            attribute. The default value is: <code>&lt;usg
                type=&quot;hint&quot;&gt;&lt;/usg&gt;</code>. The default attribute value should be
            used when it is not possible to otherwise classify the usage label. The type of a
                <gi>usg</gi> should be thought of as a conceptual axis (independent from other
            types) along which the given value of the element is located.</p>
        <p>The following list of label types and their definitions is adapted from <ref
                target="#Salgado2019b">Salgado et al. 2019b</ref>: <list>
                <item>
                    <term>temporal label</term>: <gloss>marker which identifies the use of a given
                        lexical unit on a scale from old to new. Syn: diachronic marking; diachronic
                        information; time label.</gloss>
                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><usg type="time"></usg></egXML>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <term>geographic label</term>: <gloss>marker which identifies the place or
                        region where a lexical unit is mainly used. Some dictionaries do not
                        identify a specific place but identify that the word is not used generally
                        in every geographic area (e.g., <hi rend="italic">regionalismo</hi> in
                        Portuguese, or <hi rend="italic">покр.</hi> (abbrev. for <hi rend="italic"
                            >покрајински</hi>) in Serbian). Syn: diatopic marking; diatopic
                        information; region label.</gloss>
                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><usg type="geographic"/></egXML>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <term>domain label</term>: <gloss>marker which identifies the specialized field
                        of knowledge in which a lexical unit is mainly used. Syn: diatechnical
                        marking; domain label; field label; subject field label; topic
                        label.</gloss>
                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><usg type="domain"/></egXML>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <term>frequency label</term>: <gloss>marker which identifies the relative rate
                        of occurrence of a lexical unit in a given textual context. Syn:
                        diafrequential marking; diafrequential information </gloss>
                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="inline"><usg type="frequency"/></egXML>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <term>textType label</term>: <gloss>marker which identifies the typical use of a
                        lexical unit in a particular discourse type or genre Syn: diatextual
                        information.</gloss>
                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><usg type="textType"/></egXML>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <term>attitude label</term>: <gloss>marker which identifies the speaker’s
                        subjective point of view, positive or negative, regarding the object
                        referred to by a given lexical unit. Syn: diaevaluative marking;
                        diaevaluative information.</gloss>
                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><usg type="attitude"/></egXML>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <term>socioCultural label</term>: <gloss>marker which identifies the use of a
                        given lexical unit by particular social groups and/or in certain types of
                        communicative situations depending on their level of formality Syn:
                        diaphasic marking; diaphasic information. </gloss>
                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><usg type="socioCultural"/></egXML>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <term>meaningType label</term>: <gloss>marker which identifies a semantic
                        extension of the sense of a given lexical unit.</gloss>
                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><usg type="meaningType"/></egXML>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <term>normativity label</term>: <gloss>marker which identifies the use of a
                        given lexical unit which is in some aspect considered to be non-standard or
                        incorrect.</gloss>
                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><usg type="normativity"/></egXML>
                </item>
            </list>
        </p>

        <p>The TEI <hi rend="italic">Guidelines</hi> offer a range of sample values for types to
            illustrate potential uses of <gi>usg</gi>, but not al of them have been carried over to
            TEI Lex-0. The following table shows the differences between suggested values of
                <att>type</att> in TEI and the required values of <att>type</att> in TEI Lex-0:</p>
        <table rend="pure-table pure-table-bordered">
            <row role="label">
                <cell>TEI P5 (suggested types)</cell>
                <cell>TEI Lex-0 (required types)</cell>
                <cell>Еxample values</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>time</cell>
                <cell>temporal</cell>
                <cell>archaic, old</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>geo</cell>
                <cell>geographic</cell>
                <cell>AmE., dial.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>dom</cell>
                <cell>domain</cell>
                <cell>Med., Biol., Phys.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>plev</cell>
                <cell>frequency</cell>
                <cell>rare, occas.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>-</cell>
                <cell>textType</cell>
                <cell>bibl., poet., admin., journalese</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>-</cell>
                <cell>attitude</cell>
                <cell>derog., euph.</cell>
            </row>

            <row>
                <cell>reg</cell>
                <cell>socioCultural</cell>
                <cell>slang, vulgar, formal</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>style</cell>
                <cell>meaningType</cell>
                <cell>fig. (=figurative), lit. (= literal)</cell>
            </row>

            <row>
                <cell>-</cell>
                <cell>normativity</cell>
                <cell>non-standard, incorrect</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>lang</cell>
                <cell>-</cell>
                <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>gram</cell>
                <cell>-</cell>
                <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>syn</cell>
                <cell>-</cell>
                <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>hyper</cell>
                <cell>-</cell>
                <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>colloc</cell>
                <cell>-</cell>
                <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>comp</cell>
                <cell>-</cell>
                <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>obj</cell>
                <cell>-</cell>
                <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>subj</cell>
                <cell>-</cell>
                <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>verb</cell>
                <cell>-</cell>
                <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>hint</cell>
                <cell>hint</cell>
                <cell/>
            </row>
        </table>
        <p>In TEI-Lex-0:</p>
        <list type="ordered">
            <item>The <att>type</att> attribute is made mandatory.</item>
            <item>The element <gi>usg</gi> is used in a narrower sense than is currently the case in
                the TEI <hi rend="italic">Guidelines</hi>.</item>
            <item>The <att>norm</att> attribute is encouraged.</item>
        </list>
        <p>Justification:</p>
        <list type="ordered">
            <item>Without <att>type</att> attribute, <gi>usg</gi> would be an underspecified
                element. Usage labels describe a wide range of linguistic phenomena. Classifying
                them should be considered a good practice.</item>
            <item>Currently, the TEI <hi rend="italic">Guidelines</hi> contain an overuse of
                    <gi>usg</gi> for describing phenomena that could be covered by alternative, more
                narrowly defined TEI elements. It should be considered a good practice to use the
                most specific TEI element available. See table above and the next section <ref
                    target="#RestristingUsg">Restricting the scope of <gi>usg</gi></ref></item>
            <item>It is good practice to normalize the values of the <gi>usg</gi> elements because
                dictionaries are not always consistent in the way they use their usage labels. For
                instance, abbreviated and unabbreviated labels can appear in the same dictionary:
                they should be normalized to a single value. Normalization should be only restricted
                to a single dictionary. A global normalization effort is currently beyond the scope
                of TEI Lex-0.</item>
        </list>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="RestristingUsg">
        <head>Restricting the scope of <gi>usg</gi>
        </head>
        <list type="ordered">
            <item><p>Do not use <tag>usg type="lang"</tag> to mark up the name of a language in an
                    etymological or other discussion. The recommended way to encode this information
                    is using <gi>lang</gi> element within <gi>etym</gi>.</p>
                <p>INCORRECT</p>
                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="false">
                    <entryFree xml:id="MZ.RGJS.сајдисльк_1">
                        <form type="lemma"><orth>сајдисль́к</orth></form>
                        <gramGrp><gram type="pos">м</gram></gramGrp>
                        <usg type="lang">тур.</usg>
                        <sense>
                            <def>уважавање.</def> … </sense>
                    </entryFree>
                </egXML>
                <p>CORRECT</p>
                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="d1e3815">
                    <xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml" corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="MZ.RGJS.сајдисльк_2"/>
                </egXML>
            </item>

            <item>Do not use <code>&lt;usg type=&quot;hyper&quot;&gt;&lt;/usg&gt;</code> or
                    <code>&lt;usg type=&quot;syn&quot;/&gt;</code> to mark lexical relations such as
                hyperonymy or synonymy. The recommended way to encode lexical relations in TEI Lex-0
                the reference mechanism provided by <gi>xr</gi>. See the secion on the <ref target="#cross-references"
                    >typology of cross-references.</ref>.</item>
            <item>Do not use <code>&lt;usg type=&quot;colloc&quot;&gt;&lt;/usg&gt;</code> or for
                that matter "comp.", "obj.", "subj.", "verb" etc., to encode collocations or
                rection information. See TODO.</item>
            <item><code>&lt;usg type=&quot;hint&quot;&gt;&lt;/usg&gt;</code>
                should be used as fallback for cases where the usage information does not fall into
                one of the recognized cases discussed above; or as an intermediate solution during
                the process of encoding the dictionary automatically. </item>
            <item>Frequency information on lexicographic entities may differ from other types of
                usage information in that it often cannot be interpreted without further context. In
                phrases such as “mostly biology” or “rarely used in American English” it serves the
                purpose of a modifier (quantifier) to another usage information (or other lexical
                information). Such use calls for modeling the frequency information as an attribute
                to the usg element modified. For frequency information provided explicitly (e.g.
                corpus frequencies), a separate element should be introduced. TODO</item>
        </list>
        <p><hi>Also TODO:</hi></p>
        <list type="unordered">
            <item>Frequency and source corpus? ie. source attribute &lt;usg type=”frequency” unit=???? source= “this_and_that_corpus”&gt;12&lt;/usg&gt;  </item>
        </list>

    </div>
   
</div>
