<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../css/tei_oxygen.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../css/tei.lex0.odd.css"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:teix="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="contribute">
    <head>Frequently Asked Questions</head>

    <div>
        <head>How do I start using TEI Lex-0 in my project?</head>
        <p>To start using TEI Lex-0 in your own dictionary project, you need to set up your favorite
            XML editor to validate your dictionary against the TEI Lex-0 schema. This, you can
            do:</p>
        <list>
            <item>
                <hi rend="italic">in oXygen XML Editor</hi>, by associating an existing TEI document
                with the TEI Lex-0 schema's url:
                    <code>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/DARIAH-ERIC/lexicalresources/master/Schemas/TEILex0/out/TEILex0.rng</code>
                using either menubar actions (Document > Schema > Associate Schema) or the red-pin
                icon in the oXygen menu bar. Both of these methods will display the Associate Schema
                dialog box: <figure xml:id="oxy-assoc-schema">
                    <head>Associating schema in oXygen XML Editor</head>
                    <graphic url="https://imgur.com/Z11TTWf.png"/>

                </figure>
            </item>
            <item>
                <hi rend="italic">manually</hi> by including the following xml processing
                instructions at the top of your TEI file:
                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt; 
&lt;?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/DARIAH-ERIC/lexicalresources/master/Schemas/TEILex0/out/TEILex0.rng" 
    type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?&gt;
&lt;?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" 
    type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?&gt;
&lt;TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"&gt;<!--etc.--> 
&lt;/TEI&gt;
</egXML>
            </item>
            <item>by downloading the schema file from
                    <code>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/DARIAH-ERIC/lexicalresources/master/Schemas/TEILex0/out/TEILex0.rng</code>
                and associating your xml file with it, using either of the above mentioned methods
                (see <ptr target="#oxy-assoc-schema"/>). </item>
        </list>
        <p>Once you associate your dictionary file with the TEI Lex-0 schema, you can use your XML
            editor to validate it.</p>
    </div>

    <div>
        <head>What should I do if I don't know how to encode something in TEI Lex-0?</head>
        <p>TEI Lex-0 is a community-based project. If you have a question or need help encoding
            lexicographic data using TEI Lex-0, get in touch using our <ref
                target="https://github.com/DARIAH-ERIC/lexicalresources/issues">issue tracker</ref>
            here on GitHub.</p>
    </div>

    <div>
        <head>How can I contribute to the development of TEI Lex-0?</head>
        <p>More advanced users can propose solutions by submitting pull requests. Make sure you
            understand the internal nitty-gritty as well as our GitHub workflow.</p>
    <div>
        <head>The internal nitty-gritty</head>

        <list>
            <item><code>TEILex0.odd</code> is an index file: it uses a bunch of
                    <code>&lt;xi:include&gt;</code> pointers to individual "chapters" which live in
                    <code>TEILex0.parts</code></item>
            <item> examples of dictionary entries encoded in TEI Lex-0 live in a file called
                    <code>examples.xml</code> inside the folder <code>TEILex0.examples</code></item>
            <item><code>examples.xml</code> validates against the TEI Lex-0 schema compiled in
                    <code>out/TEILex0.rng</code></item>
            <item><code>stylesheets/tei-stripper.xsl</code> is used to strip the TEI examples file
                of the TEI namespace, replacing it with "http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" so that
                they can be used directly inside <gi>egXML</gi> in our ODD file. For more info about
                why this is necessary, see <ref
                    target="https://github.com/BCDH/tei-strip-and-include"
                    >https://github.com/BCDH/tei-strip-and-include</ref>. </item>
            <item>to include validated examples, you can either point to the id of the element you
                want to include using the <code>xpointer()</code> scheme like this:
                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> 
&lt;egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"&gt; 
  &lt;xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml" 
      corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml" xpointer="pflaume"/&gt;
&lt;/egXML&gt; 
                </egXML>
                or, using the <code>element()</code> scheme, you can also include segments:
                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> 
&lt;egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"&gt; 
  &lt;xi:include href="../TEILex0.examples/examples.stripped.xml"
      corresp="../TEILex0.examples/examples.xml"
      xpointer="element(MZ.RGJS.сејче/4/1)"/> 
&lt;/egXML&gt; </egXML>
            </item>
            <item>If you are using oXygen XML, clicking on the link in Author Mode will take you
                directly to the element or fragment in the <code>examples.xml</code> for editing
                XML. <figure>
                    <graphic url="https://i.imgur.com/BLvHW45.png"/>
                    <head>testing captions</head>
                </figure>
            </item>
            <item> After making any changes to <code>examples.xml</code>, use the
                    <code>tei-stripper.xsl</code> (or the include TEI Stripper transformation
                scenario in oXygen) to produce <code>examples.stripped.xml</code>. Without this
                step, the examples in your ODD file will not validate.</item>
        </list>
    </div>
    <div>
        <head>GitHub Workflow</head>
        <p>Before submitting your proposal to change something in the TEI Lex-0 specification or the
            narrative guidelines, make sure: <list>
                <item>you have received some feedback from the community using our GitHub
                    issues</item>
                <item>you understand the internal nitty-gritty of how the TEI Lex-0 source files are
                    organized and how the guidelines and the RNG schema is generated from ODD</item>
            </list>
        </p>
        <p>To implement changes, make sure to follow our GitHub forklow: <list>
                <item>if you're starting for the first time, fork the lexical-resources repository;
                    then clone your fork on your machine; the cloned fork is your so-called working
                    copy; the original repository from which you made your clone is called
                    "upstream"</item>
                <item>if you've forked and cloned the lexical-resources repository before, make sure
                    the master branch in your working copy is up-to-date by fetching the latest
                    changes and merging them into your working master branch from the upstream
                    master</item>
                <item>create a new branch off your master branch; name it appropriately (e.g.
                    fix-attr-values-on-sense)</item>
                <item>do the work (changing the specification, adding examples, or changing the
                    narrative sections) in the specific branch you created for this particular
                    issue</item>
                <item>commit and push your changes</item>
                <item>once you've finished implementing all the changes needed, create a
                    pull-request</item>
                <item>if editors ask you to make additional changes, keep working in the same branch
                    (i.e. fix-attr-values-on-sense); commit and push; your changes will be
                    automatically added to your pull request</item>
                <item>once the editors accept your pull request, you can safely delete the branch
                    from which you created your pull request (i.e. fix.attr-values-on-sense)</item>
                <item>once your pull request has been merged into the upstream master branch by the
                    editors, you can bring the master branch in your working copy up to date by
                    fetching and merging changes from upstream master; then pushing them to your
                    remote repo</item>
            </list>
        </p>
    </div>
    </div>
<div>
    <head>How can I convert dictionaries from TEI Lex-0 to Ontolex-Lemon?</head>
    <p>Funny you should ask, because we have exactly what you're looking for. Check out the <ref target="https://github.com/elexis-eu/tei2ontolex">tei2ontolex</ref> stylesheet. </p>
</div>


</div>
