<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../css/tei_oxygen.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../css/tei.lex0.odd.css"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="introduction">
    <head>Introduction</head>
    <p>Achieving consistent encoding within a given community of practice has been a
        recurrent issue for the TEI Guidelines. The topic is of particular importance
        for lexical data if we think of the potential wealth of content we could gain
        from pooling together the information available in the variety of highly
        structured, historical and contemporary lexical resources. Still, the encoding
        possibilities offered by the Dictionaries Chapter in the Guidelines are too
        numerous and too flexible to guarantee sufficient interoperability and a
        coherent model for searching, visualising or enriching multiple lexical
        resources.</p>
    <p>Following the spirit of TEI Analytics [Zillig, 2009], developed in the context of
        the MONK project, <hi rend="bold">TEI Lex-0</hi> aims at establishing a baseline
        encoding and a target format to facilitate the interoperability of
        heterogeneously encoded lexical resources. This is important both in the context
        of building lexical infrastructures as such [Ermolaev and Tasovac, 2012] and in
        the context of developing generic TEI-aware tools such as dictionary viewers and
        profilers. T</p>
    <p>TEI Lex-0 should not be thought of as a replacement of the Dictionary Chapter in
        the TEI Guidelines or as the format that must be used for editing or managing
        individual resources, especially in those projects and/or institutions that
        already have established workflows based on their own flavors of TEI. TEI Lex-0
        should be primarily seen as a format that existing TEI dictionaries can be
        univocally transformed to in order to be queried, visualised, or mined in a
        uniform way. At the same time, however, there is no reason why TEI Lex-0 could
        not or should not be used as a best-practice example in educational settings or
        as a set of best-practice guidelines for new TEI-based projects, especially
        considering the fact that in TEI Lex-0 we aimed to stay as aligned as possible
        with the TEI subset developed in conjunction with the revision of the ISO LMF
        (Lexical Markup Framework) standard (cf. [Romary, 2015])</p>
    <div>
        <head>Context</head>
        <p>Preliminary work for the establishment of TEI Lex-0 started in the Working
            Group "Retrodigitised Dictionaries" lead by Toma Tasovac and Vera
            Hildenbrandt as part of the COST Action <ref
                target="http://www.elexicography.eu">European Network of
                e-Lexicography</ref> (ENeL). Upon the completion of the COST Action, the
            work on TEI Lex-0 was taken up by the DARIAH Working Group "Lexical
            Resources" which is co-chaired by Laurent Romary and Toma Tasovac.
            Currently, the work on TEI Lex-0 is conducted by the DARIAH WG "Lexical
            Resources" and the H2020-funded <ref target="https://elex.is">European
                Lexicographic Infrastructure</ref> (ELEXIS). </p>
        
    </div>
    <div>
        <head>Dictionary model vs. XML serialization</head>
        <p>A fundamental principle that the present enterprise relies on is the nature
            of the mapping of the physical or “near-physical” (OCR-ed) dictionary
            contents onto the abstract model of a dictionary structure, and the mapping
            from said model onto its (in our case) TEI XML serialization. It is
            important to keep in mind the distinction between the abstract model and its
            serialization because, as we shall see, the TEI uses the same elements of
            the abstract model to serve many kinds of text-modelling tasks, and
            standardly employs ‘features’ or ‘facets’ of these elements (known in the
            XML world as attributes) to express differences among them. The fact that
            some elements of the serialization have names closely corresponding to what
            we can customarily find in the dictionary model is more or less a lucky
            coincidence. It is not the pattern to be expected. A lexicographer coming
            from outside of the TEI universe should not necessarily expect his or her
            customary terms (names of dictionary objects in the dictionary model) to be
            straightforwardly reflected in the TEI vocabulary names.</p>
        <p>Take, for instance, the TEI element <gi>cit</gi>. Originally, its TEI name
            came from the word “citation” and this is what the element was used for up
            to the early days of TEI P5, when it acquired a new, broader function of
            grouping together pieces of text perceived or broadly treated as “foreign”
            or additional, together with their (bibliographic, linguistic, or
            usage-oriented) description. This element is nowadays used as a “container”
            for citations, dictionary examples, translation equivalents etc. The value
            of the attribute <att>type</att> is used to further specify the kind of
            cit-object at hand. In our case, four distinct names of dictionary objects
            in the abstract dictionary model (namely, “citation”, “example”,
            “translation” (of quotes) and “translation equivalent” (of words) map onto
            four distinct element+attribute combinations in the TEI XML serialization
            (respectively, <gi>cit</gi> with <att>type</att>="citation", <gi>cit</gi>
            with <att>type</att>="example", and <gi>cit</gi> with
            <att>type</att>="translation" or
            <att>type</att>="translationEquivalent".</p>
        <p>The following example from a bilingual dictionary, shows how one typed
            element – <gi>cit</gi> – can be used to encode different parts of the
            dictionary structure:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <xi:include href="../TEILex0.odd.examples/TEILex0-examples.stripped.xml" xpointer="horrifier"
                corresp="../TEILex0.odd.examples/TEILex0-examples.xml"/>
        </egXML>
        
        
    </div>
</div>
